hello and welcome to voice club welcome
to Bristol behind me and welcome to in a
few moments time the foothills of Prague
where melissa warner speaks with rick
doblin it's a wonderful conversation I
hope you very much enjoy it here we go
you
[Music]
and you'd be an engine of change in the
movement solidifying psychedelics is
tools of personal healing and
transformation it's being a life's work
I know knowing you the creative advance
will continue mm-hmm well we're not
there yet
if ever know about this point in time as
you said recently in your talk here at
beyond psychedelics we have more cyclic
research now than the last 50 years so I
want to start with the question what has
motivated you to make this your life's
work fear I wasn't expecting that
yeah I've been able to try to turn fear
into motivation so kind of a not
overwhelming fear but it's fear of
insanity resulting in mass murder and
nuclear annihilation and environmental
destruction all of which are real
possibilities hopefully none of them are
likely but they're all moving in that
direction towards so it was fear of the
Holocaust fear of the Cuban Missile
Crisis and fear of Vietnam and what our
country was doing that all made me think
that the overall trends were bad and
that my parents were gonna pay for my
food and shelter I had that sense that
they would support me in that way
whatever I wanted to do because I am you
know dropped out of college at 18 after
doing a lot of LSD and told him I want
him I wanted to study LSD outside of
college on my own and I wanted them to
pay for it Jewish families yes right and
so you had a sense of the idea of
multi-generational trauma
growing up yeah what was it like to grow
up well I think that for me in some ways
the trauma was terrifying
but I was struggling to understand it
from a position of incredible safety and
I've realized that I we talk about white
privilege you know but I think I had I
had every almost every possible of
privilege you could have so I grew up
first off you know with this American
exceptionalism that America had won the
war that we were the most powerful
country in the world and in some part of
me believed that it was because we were
better people or something you know that
were exceptional or that the you know
the political system obviously is what's
exceptional that more cooperation and
competition but yes I just grew up this
way of this American exceptionalism like
I grew up with this sense of being white
being assimilated Jews you know where we
lived my parents had a house built when
I was twelve that was designed by a
student of Frank Lloyd Wright's but it
was in land in a suburb of Chicago that
they wouldn't sell to Jews and so there
was this piece of four parcels of land
that this for Jewish families got a
Christian family to buy the land for
them and then sell it to them so that's
how we so we even went to a place where
Jews weren't welcome but I didn't know
that kind of till later growing up no I
felt like I remember in the past that
World War Two was way in the past and
that this kind of prejudice against
American Jews were way in the past so I
grew up with the Jews as chosen people
but something made it made it prevalent
for you this you sense this sense of
fear the sense of you know wanting to
assure a positive future and move away
from I guess what these possibilities
had occurred in your family's ancestry
yeah I think it was that I felt so safe
again that my parents my grandparents I
felt it's just like I had every
opportunity to do whatever I wanted and
and so I could kind of look at not like
a lot of people have to think initially
you know survival how do i you know earn
money to survive and I felt like my
family would provide survival so that I
could look at the next
of threats thriving thriving but also
yeah thriving in the face of the real
challenges yeah what did you read what
did you what was the experience that led
you to the point of saying psychedelics
would be a tool for assuring a more
positive future well I was a big big
reader so I was super shy in high school
and so there was a year ago I didn't
even say a word to a girl other than to
my sister and mother and so I was living
in books a lot and so I started the
first book I ever read was called the
Cannes Cannes mutiny and it was
historical kind of fiction but it was
about a domineering captain on a ship
where they have ultimate authority and
it was a mutiny among the men during
during wartime and it was just one
person against you know against an
oppressive system but that was the book
that turned me around really the key one
was one Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest by
Ken Kesey that on LSD he did but I
didn't know that till after I read it
and so I read it and thought it was
fantastic again what about the message
of the book message of the book is that
there's this combine in the system
that's trying to control things and the
individuals who stick out there's some
pressure to crush them and how do you
the price you pay for trying to be your
own unique self and the importance of
struggling you know and in some ways the
importance of quiet and laying low like
chief broom who was watching you know
the destruction of the hero but I just
thought it was fantastic
and was shocked when some of it was
written on LSD so change of perspective
I know like if there's no way somebody
could write this
an LSD based on what I have been told
that was DJO it told that physically
back then when he goes you would grow
half the point where the laws were
changing and all the research was being
shut down yeah you know there was so
much promise in the study of addiction
in a study of depression and also for
enhancing creativity but shifting the
culture was causing these walls just
just sort of come around these compounds
yeah so you came in and right at that
point yeah and then the other things
that I was reading I was starting to
read more Eastern mysticism I read a lot
of Hermann Hesse and Jung and Freud and
what I I Aldous Huxley and so I would
read I tried to read everything somebody
wrote my grandparents had a bookstore
I love the Huxley quote psychedelics on
the plane of Perpetual creation they may
serve to heal mental illness in the
future and that is a future that you're
bringing to fruition yeah yeah yeah
we're trying to we as a large group of
people trying to bring psychedelic
medicines into the mainstream what is it
about the psychedelic experience that
you feel connects people to a sense of
meaning and a flexibility in which I can
orient themselves towards change and
well in your early experiences what led
you to go AHA this is where I'm going to
donate my energies yeah well the first
time I ever took LSD you know you hear
so much about this mystical experience
and beyond ego states and how it you
know at the time it was mostly like the
time I was doing starting to do LSD a
standard dose was 250 micrograms right
now a standard dose of LSD is like 60 or
70 micrograms or it's a lot less but it
was designed to have these overwhelming
mystical experiences and that was
considered one dose and so I had a lot
of expectations of what that would be
like and I also had a lot of
disappointment from my bar mitzvah which
I had thought would be a transformative
experience but really wasn't
and so the first things I started
noticing when I was under the influence
of LSD for that was the way in which
there was different kind of depths of my
feelings you know this kind of very
thoughtful I mean way that I proceeded
very you know above my emotional life
but in a way so I could look at because
I was so scared and so much fear it was
it woke me up to my emotions yeah we
often are out of touch with our emotions
I don't really know we're not taught how
to interpret them how to handle them and
there is definitely and I myself have
coming from a scientific background
I very much stand on the side growing up
of a rationality and what can be
calculated what we can figure out and I
think that there is a sense that the
mystical experience what does it mean
and what is the one of the more
irrational emotional parts of our brain
that are definitely there and need to be
recognized how do we best approach them
and sort them out in a way that allows
us to access our best selves and
psychedelics definitely can be tools for
those I have really enjoyed some of your
stories of your experiences have really
enabled me to contact those both both
sides of myself I particularly think of
the story you told me about how
psychedelics helped you communicate with
your inner critic that voice and we we
all we all have that always knows what
we could have done better but not really
doesn't really show us how can you tell
us about that experience I'd be glad to
even though it was very difficult it was
at the time when in 1985 when we were
just starting to sue the DEA and so
there's hello Leo's F that was the we
call him the secret chief the leader of
underground psychotherapy who really
helped introduce MDMA he said to me that
as long as I was starting to do more
political work he wanted me to do an
experience with ibogaine that he thought
would help me for my own shadow and
ibogaine is quite different from other
psychedelics isn't it
it's used for this healing of addiction
yeah I'd say it's more similar than
different in the sense that it does give
you a broader perspective there's
enhanced imagery yeah I I think the
difference is it's somehow more
instinctual it feels like people talk
about it as like their ancestors are
more LSD feels like what clear and clean
up in the head kind of and psilocybin is
a little bit more embodied mescaline
that way too and just by gains are quite
a long experience as well it's very long
and so and it takes a long time to come
on so Leo said that he wanted to
administer it with LSD so it was 350
micrograms of LSD and about four grams
of total alkaloid ibogaine and so the
essence of it was though that I realized
this inner critic and just felt that the
connection between self-criticism and
self-hatred and I got into this whole
thing every time I would see that I
would kind of feel nauseous even more
the LSD part went smooth kind of through
this opening and through the peak of it
and I don't actually you know recall all
that much of that LSD part of it because
it was all about this sense of being
appalled at the amount of self-hatred
hatred that I have for myself and then I
would vomit and then we become aware of
it it can be quite shocking that little
voice is this always there itis subtly
letting us know that we're not doing
good enough right now how did how did
that shift how do this create a shift
into a new relationship yeah well I saw
that the image I had was as a Jewish
person that I was being crucified on the
cross of self perfectionism and I just
would see that and uh and because the
worst part was I would say that and I
was doing it to myself not only that if
I could just relax and get over it I
just didn't know how and so the way that
I got through it was I never could
actually
so what happened was I just vomited for
like 10 12 10 hours or so just really
feeling this trap this horror part of it
and then I got exhausted and so I know
that transcendence through exhaustion I
think the old eel experience is
something is quite relevant to
psychedelics a concept that by facing
something is challenging so it shows us
that we can be so much more we can
overcome I think that's very true but
but I also think that there's ways we
make the ordeal even harder I mean if it
you know I what what happened for me was
just I somehow got all exhausted from
that process and I just moved into the
opposite of this openness and
self-acceptance and most blissful
peaceful the whole night and I was a
place where it was on the water and I
could see the stars and I just was part
of this beautiful peaceful accepting
process but I felt that I had not earned
it
I hadn't like made that turned the
switch to turn it off all of this self I
just said and so I thought that when the
Sun comes up and the tide comes in that
I would be back stocked that this was
like grace it was like yeah Trenton and
that's actually what happened so the
next day I was I couldn't even sit up
without feeling nauseous I couldn't eat
I had to lie down I couldn't even leave
I was supposed to leave the next day I
had to stay there the whole day finally
barelly somebody came to me on the third
day to take me home take me somewhere
else and it wasn't till the fourth day
that I could drive but what I felt had
happened was that I had more space in my
mind I could pay more attention to what
was happening outside and also that I
needed that self-critic that the thing
was that I need you need that
self-critic to help you think about what
you can do until learn is just learning
and you wouldn't even have those lessons
if you hadn't done things which you can
be proud of yourself for having tried
something even if it fails and so I
could say yeah I can make a friend of
the self-critic
and also by virtue of that get
more and more of the ideas aways
self-improvement and then the other idea
is that you've missed the opportunity
you've blown it in that moment never
comes back again and I started seeing
about how there were all these second
chances that you could you couldn't put
it into practice in that moment that
moment is gone but there's similar kind
of moments or situations sometimes with
different people sometimes with even the
same people and so that I've since
that's 1985 and I felt that it's a major
extent the success that vamps has had is
because it's been more easy for me to
learn from my mistakes in fact I call
myself just a fuckup who just keeps
trying to succeed you have to learn how
to fail better each time there has to be
a degree of self-acceptance in that
process to view that and I really like
how you describe this experience with a
sense of turning that inner critic and
into it into a mentor yeah
they'll have changing that relationship
and we can all do with ourselves yeah
and you have to be a little bit gentle
on yourself like yeah it's yeah and I
think this and be proud of the actions
don't we and that's what psychedelics
help us do yeah very much but
particularly if there's a supportive
setting yes that's very important at a
therapeutic setting not only therapeutic
supportive supportive yeah like what do
you think of the key ingredients for
that setting well let's say that that
you're surrounded by a safe place where
you could go inward you could close your
eyes you could lie in the ground and you
could be defenseless from the outside
but that you could explore wherever your
mind or feelings were taking you that
you're in that safe place and also the
attitude that you're open to whatever
happens the that you can have a plan but
you're sort of unconscious the rest of
your mind has a deeper plan or a deeper
sense of need in a heal or something
it's very important in psychedelic
healing this this natural intelligence
that our unconscious minds do seem to
have about the direction that we need to
go I'm quite curious to hear more about
the experiences in the MDMA trials
for PTSD and encounters with this in a
Gila okay yeah I just had on that last
question that it that I think you could
have this openness to whatever would
happen in the sense of safety outdoors
in a dance party with you know friends
around you or you could have it indoors
in a treatment center or you can have it
camping out by yourself or with a few
friends it's a little bit harder to do
by yourself because you really need to
feel safe in that spot but it's good to
have someone that's a mediator between
world and the other sitter isn't on the
psychedelic you can create that safe
space yeah and where it could be in a
church so I guess what I want to say is
that there could be medical use there
could be religious use there could be
ceremonial use recreational well people
or something it's a very important
concept in cyclic world as well yeah
this is not just something to heal
illness but to improve the meaning and
allies in our relationship to ourselves
yeah one way to think about it is that
we might be well but we're not all that
well there's a lot of ways we could be
more well self-actualization I think is
a goal post it's going to keep moving
yeah and also even if we're well I mean
just when you think about what's
happening to the earth and the species
and the massive die-off and the threats
you have to spend some time feeling
painful and so you know if you're well
you're processing massive trauma and
murder and horrible things you know and
risk it out don't we yeah yeah it's hard
to function but I think that's so I
think maybe the idea of betterment of
well people or not actually all that
well yeah a lot of us some I mean or and
and what that does though is that gets
into the discussion about prohibition
and post religious freedom post medical
use limitations which are valuable and
crucial we are going in those ways but
there is this bigger a sense of need and
importance and
human rights and freedom yeah we can
come back to the healer just because
we've gone down this path and I'm also
taking it back to the beginning idea of
multi-generational trauma I think it's a
really important point for both our
countries Australia and the United
States having a history of trauma in our
First Nations people well even the whole
Australia being founded by prisoners
being sent there
you know exiled so you're a country of X
Isles and you know now bad criminals
type change changing our storylines is
something psychedelics are really
helpful for I guess and that can be
hacked that can happen on an individual
level or on on a wider scale yeah yeah
so like some of the examples of an inner
healer in the studies a lot of it has
have been about forgiveness of others
actually yes oh yeah I think forgiveness
is a gift that you give yourself
actually yeah
yeah it's one of the ways to set
yourself free from trauma and I'm quite
curious to hear more about your thoughts
on that yeah well one of the Israeli
doctors the when we were first starting
to try to do the project in Israel we've
done it in multiple sites he was a
traditional psychiatrist and he asked
this question which was is this for the
victims or the perpetrators and he said
I don't think this should be this would
work for perpetrators and and I said no
that's not the case at all that it's
harder sometimes to forgive ourselves
and just to forgive other people and so
what we've seen is that people can
forgive perpetrators they can see the
pain that drove people to do things
horrible things to them they can see
that but then they can also you know
people might blame themselves for
getting in those situations or then they
can forgive themselves and there's a
huge aspect of trauma feeling like there
is always something more you could have
done to avoid the situation is led to
you feeling this way of feeling trapped
in your own mind
yeah one person had said that the
perpetrator told her that if she ever
told anybody about what happened he
would kill her
that was in an MDMA yeah yeah yeah no
that was a prior obsession but but
speaking about it was liberating you
know that the fear was carried that
whole time there's ways in which people
some of the veterans have killed
innocent people yes in war networks what
happens yeah and they were scared and
they were made quick judgments that were
wrong and so particularly one that had
killed two little girls that kill the
they were driving and the father was
driving and wouldn't stop and he
couldn't figure it out so just forgiving
themselves now I think there's a edge
it's not like they think they did the
right thing it's not like people have
said to me are you making war easier are
you making it easier for soldiers to do
horrible things and then just take MDMA
and then they're fine and they're gonna
go out and do them again and so I think
it's important to say that it was
forgiving but not thinking that it was
okay it was something that they had to
accept and move on not so much
forgiving doesn't mean saying it didn't
matter it wasn't okay no of course not I
feel like getting in touch with the
roots of your trauma knowing where they
occurred if this was in war I think it
would probably have the opposite
reaction that you wouldn't want to be
going back it's not like II I put on a
band-aid trauma fix that send you back
to the frontlines no that's I can't
imagine that would be the reaction of
any of the soldiers in the trials is
that well I think the difference is that
if you believe in the mission you know
that's the question is like if you were
in a war for survival and somebody and
you got wounded and you needed to take
some time to get emotionally patched up
and you felt that everything was that a
threat you might go back to the war but
if you don't really believe in the
mission like with Iraq the invasion of
Iraq is our optional war and a lot of
people grew to see that we weren't how
and that it was not welcome and that
they didn't believe in the mission so I
think because we've had these
discussions with the Department of
Defense and other people it's like the
sooner you can treat people to the
trauma the better which means moving
from veterans to active-duty soldiers if
you can or moving from people that have
had PTSD from a childhood and then
waiting till they get adults and then
treating them you know actually I mean
the FDA is requiring us to do pediatric
studies once we complete the studies and
adults so I think this saturating
childhood trauma yeah very much so
well one of the friends that was at the
conference here Torsten pass II was like
what happens if you were doing MDMA
therapy long ago and a Nazi
concentration camp guard said they
needed help would you treat them you
know is that just you know they're doing
this inhumane thing and you just help
process and they go back and they you
know show more people in the gas chamber
I mean that was his his worry is that
happening and so I think that it's not
likely to be that yeah I think when you
get sensitized to the emotional
consequences of what you're doing if you
don't believe in it it'll make it harder
to do
I think as totally relevant for veterans
but also victims of sexual assault and
domestic abuse there's a sense that I
know one person who experienced a rape
and she was concerned that if she was to
use only made a heal she wouldn't just
be healing herself that she would be
losing her sense of injustice towards
her abuse I through our conversation I
sort of communicated to her that
liberating herself from the rigidity
that trauma causes around our
functioning this frozen state in time
that's what it is it's an attractant in
time we'll actually free her to do work
in the world to change the mechanisms
that have in society that led to this
mentality of the men who perpetrated the
abuse against her it's a I'm quite
interested to hear your thoughts on on
the other side of trauma which is stuff
that happens in in everyone's lives
domestic abuse sexual assault of women
and what Maps is doing in regards to
that side of trauma yeah because there's
way more trauma from those causes then
from war and and I think sometimes
people lose sight of that because we're
just talking a lot about the veterans
but I'm curious did your friend actually
try MDMA and what impact did it have if
she did she did try it and it had a very
positive impact it did reveal in fact
she didn't even have memories of it but
her trauma had gone right back into
childhood and she was able to realize
these patterns that had led to her
eventual rape more recent sexual assault
where she was fulfilling these these
rigid behavioral roles since her
childhood and she was able to leave the
environment that she was in that was a
dangerous one where she was actually
still living with the perpetrator Wow
yes so very positive effect okay so it
didn't make her excuse it like it's okay
and she worked very hard on cultivating
a lot of research about the nature of
sexual abuse and the prevalence of it in
society after the rape I think I think
that
MDMA actually made it easier for her to
tackle those issues and to deal with
something it would be quite triggering
otherwise and she used that knowledge to
empower and to teach other women yeah
we've had a lot of people have said
we'll MDMA work with complex trauma
where people are abused as a child and
they're continually raised in this
abusive environment as opposed to just
like a one-time sexual assault or
something like that and so we've had a
lot of people that have had that chronic
kind of complex trauma that still have
been able to be healed with
mdma-assisted therapy and the way in
which it seems to to work a lot of it is
that just a lot of its just processing
the the emotions people are when things
are happening
they tend a lot of times people tend to
dissociate so we have a measure of
dissociation and we find that those
people that are higher on dissociation
take longer to heal because it takes a
while the fear is so great that that was
their defense strategy
yes association at one point in the
trauma saved them from the full
experience of the moments in which they
were traumatized so it's a protective
mechanism which is why it you know in
the brain it's so locked in because this
is you know this is what allowed me to
survive yeah and it also helps you to
stay conscious to pay attention to ways
you might escape or ways so it's it's
not just yeah it's both helping you with
really painful emotions but also you
know definitely you know ideas that you
might get about increasing your chance
to survive yeah I think it's quite
interesting how MDMA actually is likely
to be what the mechanism is in the brain
of how it heals trauma this idea is that
by remembering the trauma in a safe
cognitive space in a sense of love and a
sense of complete ease that we can
change the emotive aspects of that
memory could you explain a bit more
about how that works
yeah there's lucky for me the
da to make a drug into a medicine you
have to prove safety and efficacy but
you don't have to prove mechanism of
action so but we do know a lot from
other people have funded mechanism
action so the emotions get frozen when
they happen there's the fear processing
part of the brain the amygdala which
over time actually in PTSD patients gets
more and more active you kind of repeat
these fear cycles stuckness yeah the
prefrontal cortex where we kind of think
logically and put things in context that
shrinks for people in PTSD their
emotional sense of self yeah and then
there's a with MDMA it almost does the
opposite it does the opposite it reduces
activity in the amygdala so you can take
fear emotions and then it increases
activity in the prefrontal cortex but
the other key part is that it increases
the connection between the hippocampus
where memories are processed and the
amygdala so fear-based memories can now
move out of this place where it's like
they're always still happening or about
to happen which is what the the yeah
what you talked about with time you know
you're sort of stuck in the past that
you haven't been able to put something
in the past and and so this movement of
memory from this kind of immediate
through processing an often that takes
place emotionally
crying but also a lot through the body
there's a expert in PTSD dr. Bessel
Vandercook yeah and his book is really
terrific and it's called the body Keith
the school yeah listening out there
yeah he's principal investigator on our
Boston site yes yeah and so what we see
a lot of times is that it comes out not
in like necessarily like realizations
but it comes out in the release of
energy in the body
people could be shaking or crying or are
just like kicking or just like for
extended periods of time sometimes
resolving what they couldn't do in the
moment yeah yeah well processing I went
yeah kind of an resolving yeah that it's
like stored all this energy that's then
released it's like you know after it
like grieving you know you can hold that
grieving and then when you cry and can
grieve than you
you know you've taken it in more and
things change and you can move on to
express those emotions can be difficult
but it is there it's very important very
much I also like the idea that MDMA the
concept that was in memory every time we
remember something
we don't just reread the file we take
out the file put it on a laptop and
retype it yeah yeah it's recreated each
time we remember something and MDMA what
may be happening is when we remember
this this moment in this context of love
and acceptance we re encode the memory
without the fear and without the pain
yeah so I was just at the Czech National
Institute of Mental Health earlier today
and they were doing you know as for
mental health and they were showing me
some of the research that they do that
with rats and they have one thing that's
called episodic memory so it's where
they're trying to see if how much rats
can remember about a particular maze and
it's it's a memory for the episode but
our memories are sort of combinations of
episodic memory and emotional memory and
so what we see with MDMA for trauma is
that the episodic memory is increased
because so much of it was linked with
pain and was forgotten or suppressed or
some conscious so people under the
influence of MDMA have an increase in
memory of what actually happened but the
emotional memory is switched around from
the panic and the fear associated in the
lack of trust in the world has changed
to a sense that you're processing it
peacefully it was in the past and so
then when the memory gets reconsolidated
it's you even have a better episodic
memory and you've switched the emotional
tone which is really important feeling
and you're growing new neurons
so there's neurogenesis there's
different pathways and we've shown that
after PTSD treatment in a bunch of
patients the amygdala activity is
actually reduced you can show physical
consequences of changes in brain and
genuine structural changes in the brain
yeah well these are just so far just
activity yeah I don't think there's been
I don't know if they've shown but yeah
there are studies now more and more
showing neurogenesis from MDMA and other
psychedelics but I don't think that the
neuroscientists have shown new
structural pathways yet maybe they
change it changing connectivity yes
bringing it back to this concept of the
mystical experience or peak experience
we see I think interchangeable terms
mystical experience and peak experience
peak experience being defined by Abraham
Maslow as a important step for
self-actualization on the hierarchy of
needs so what is it about this peak
experience that you feel connects people
to meaning in their lives and to
interchange mm-hmm
well it's so interesting you mentioned
that about Maslow so from the knees
hierarchy where you're saying the
self-actualization as being the top and
then here so it's more like your
survival needs your community social
needs and then self-actualization at the
top so the peak experience idea is
actually something that Maslow changed
his ideas over time and what he he
started humanistic psychology and that
had this kind of need hierarchy but he
also near the end of his life started
transpersonal psychology and so he
changed the need Harkey so that it was
self transcendence above
self-actualization and that's the
movement towards kind of global
spirituality or spirituality you know
that that's seeing the bigger picture
and and then it comes with that a
certain peacefulness about death and a
transcendence of time and space and so
the peak experience is meant to be this
meaning of life the sense of how we fit
into this bigger picture and but there's
many different kinds of peak experiences
you know that they're not all like some
of them are you know just doing things
that you're very proud of yes like who
you could hike and climb a mountain that
could be a big experience or
could take them milligrams of psilocybin
and that would be another form of having
a evidence-based peak experience which
has a potential to shift our lives and I
was interested in the word transpersonal
psychology is are not sure if everyone
is familiar with that and you're one of
your mentees centers of Graf yeah and
yeah how that has shaped your connection
to psychedelics and what and yeah well
the book you asked before about books
and so where I learned about
transpersonal psychology and where so I
was you know eighteen and had taken a
lot of LSD and was very confused and
knew I wanted to drop out of college and
went to the guidance counselor at my
college and said help me you know make
sense of all this all these raging
emotions and ideas and and so he gave me
realms of the human unconscious by Stan
Grof to read and that's where I first
started understanding about this
transcendence of self or the the
transpersonal means between it's like
something that we all have you know so
it's but it's beyond the personal so we
all have the confrontation with death
and we all have the need for community
and love and the need for you know all
the things in the need hurricane yeah
and so I started realizing that here was
a way through a combination of
experiments with thousands of people
under the influence of LSD where I me
Stan said that the LSD is like the
telescope to astronomy or the microscope
to biology LSD is for the mind like that
and so it's a really powerful court and
quite accurate yeah and so from all of
what he was saying here was this broad
understanding of where the psyche goes
and it goes into these there I don't
want to give up down kind of metaphors
but it it extends like a rainbow or
something into these shared kind of
spiritual areas that give you meaning
for your life and give meaning to the
daily moments
and gratitude for the chance to be alive
and that their transformative yeah I
think spiritualism can be it's a hard
word for some people particularly of a
scientific bent but we are shifting in
our relationship to that word I I love
how the neuroscientist Sam Harris has
come out with his experiences of
evidence-based spirituality if there is
such a thing
I think psychedelics look kind of relate
to that do you know what sam harris said
was his most mystical experience of his
life that he's written about MDMA MDMA
yeah you are at first empty was it your
first no no spiritual moment can you
share that with us yeah well okay so
this was at a point in time were also
not it was around the time that I had
the ibogaine experience was also in
early 85 and I had been working with
brother David Stein the wrost I mean
he'd come and taught some classes at
Esalen that Stan had organized that I
participated in and when I learned about
MD and I got I really appreciated him
he's kind of a Roman Catholic mystic
open-minded and when I was learning
about MDMA I started talking to him
about it and eventually he said he
wanted to do that in the monastery as
half doses for meditation and he was
willing to do it and so it was this
period of time where were engaged in a
fight with the DEA we're about to sue
them and also I had no relationship at
the time and so I was feeling alone and
so I decided that I would I had a power
spot at Esalen for me it was beautiful
yeah yeah yeah I spent a bunch of time
there and with sanin otherwise so
there's a creek that goes through the
property there's the big house that
there's the near the small waterfall
near where the right at the edge of the
cliffs so where that waterfall goes down
and it goes into the ocean
right on the other side of it so there's
a path from the big house that you can't
get down from the rest of esslyn which
is their rooms and the hot bath so the
the hot tubs and the where the guests
stay but across the river across the
bridge you come from the other side and
you go down to where the river is and
then you walk across it it's not that
deep and there's a little spot that's
about the size of this bench where the
mountain comes right behind and there's
enormous boulders that are you know out
in front of you ways out but so the high
tide comes right around and right to
there and I would but you could be in
this little spot surrounded by at the
most you're safe and dry the whole time
no matter what the tide does but it's
right nearby mountain behind you the
river and is safe though I felt so this
was where I decided to do MDMA by myself
at night down and camping out and just
feeling really really safe with the
universe it felt like the universe was
my front yard you know the ocean was the
front yard and the sky and so part of
the night was spent looking at a tree
and somehow imagining that the tree was
the DEA and different people were in the
tree were looking at me in different
ways and I was trying to negotiate this
idea of how do I sue the DEA and stay
safe and so I came to the conclusion
from that that that somehow they're
always looking for under the rock or
what's being hidden and if you come
directly Adam there is a certain kind of
safety event and so I felt comfortable
with that but then I started thinking
about why would brother David want to be
celibate why would anybody want I could
understand more wanting to be reflective
you know and spend time meditating and
discipline but why would somebody want
to you know not have human relationships
like that and be sahabat or not have
human sexual relationships like that and
so I just started thinking about him for
a while and just speculating on it and
then
I started thinking that here I was this
the roar of the ocean was incredible and
the the the vastness of the Stars and I
just thought man I'm so tiny compared to
all of this and and I could just the
more I beheld the bigger account I was
like I was just fly up I would lose
myself and I would just fly up and and I
thought how come after a while I
realized I was still there somehow
that there was something that was
keeping me there I didn't just fly out
into the universe and I started just
pondering the fact that it was gravity
it was the thing that holds things
together that that there was kind of a
without gravity we would all be
dispersed and everything would be you
know uniform or whatever so I felt like
this gravity was this force of love and
that it was holding things together and
then I felt it as if it was the arms of
a lover and I felt like I was being
cradled in the arms of gravity and it
was so warm and rich that I and then I
thought that's what the monastic life is
about is that if you can have this
warmth to the universe if you can
somehow you don't you know it doesn't
come from an individual it comes from
the universe and if you can feel it that
way that warm and so I felt like I
understood a bit about the monastic life
and I thought well great I've done that
with MDMA now I don't need to be
celibate so thirty years later I was at
a conference and I was able to sit next
to brother David 30 years after that and
I was like for other day but I had this
experience most spiritual experience my
life you weren't involved in it you know
and I want to just describe it to you
and see what you think of it so he said
ok so I told him that story and
afterwards he looked at me just for a
second and he said he said Rick I think
of gravity every day
he had the relationship yeah I think
it's interesting how you said you felt
like the ocean the stars were your front
yard and yet that they are we always
forget yeah I don't it wonderful when
you when you have when you feel that way
and you know it yeah and I think feeling
it is part of knowing it actually Rita
Marley who is married to Bob Marley she
had the album that's a terrific album
and the name of the album is who feels
it knows it that's the connection we're
looking for something definitely that
psychedelics can provide us yeah
and that's a great launchpad for the
rest of your life looks like I like just
tools it is one one facet of a healthy
life yeah although I would say that
there's many different journeys to be
launched on throughout your life yeah so
I see that psychedelics have a different
role at different stages of y'all I like
this point very much I myself am NOT a
fan of the Alan Watts quote that once
you get the message hang up the phone
like everything could be terrible if you
had you know never taken a female
psychedelics again after that you had
that moment of a reunion with nature
there's so much more to learn and at
different times yeah I think that
there's many different messages it's not
I think there's a certain we all want to
have the message I know the truth I've
got the message and then you can relax
but things are constantly changing I
would say one of the things that's so
terrible about Trump just to make a
pivot there is let's make America great
again
I mean you can't be great again in the
way of the past you have to be great in
response to the changing of the future
and the yeah and looking forward like
that and engaging with an evolving
process that's constantly moving
yeah and when you think I've got the
truth or I've got the message it's kind
of fixed in time and it's a lazy kind of
way of thinking actually yes also a bit
of a workout for the mind I going to
assume for the mind and they definitely
encourage your laziness do they yeah not
at all and I think the other part is
that there's some there's another part
of that that's really a misunderstanding
which is that we can see things clearly
and know anything clearly or certain
we're always seeing through filters we
have unconscious filters so we shouldn't
have confidence that we really know it's
going and you know to keep questioning
you know is important to not think I've
got it
questioning and keep trying I think very
funnily of the chain of emails we had
when we had synonyms for the word
tenacity that's a sign-off I think I
love it because it's something that you
so embody as a person and I think it's
something that we could have more of in
our lives in the way we approach our
passions in the world
can you tell us a bit how you've been
able to embody this within yourself well
one way is that you know I had this idea
when I was 18 that I wanted to devote my
life to psychedelics as a response to
both personally what I needed
well actually I'll say that at 18 I kind
of came up with this idea that there was
two things that I want to do one was to
learn how to trip and the other was to
learn how to make love and that those
are ways about inner and outer kind of
and that I want to work on both of those
that would be the judge of my life in a
way you know those would be that and so
I've never had a better idea very
important to how we approach mourning
how we approach our teen as well how we
approach our co-workers how we approach
strangers knowledge yeah and and I felt
a lot of the times too that the
resistance to psychedelics and to
integrated them into our culture was a
fear of change of fear of facing oneself
that that resistance wasn't a sign that
I was on the wrong track it was a sign I
was on the right track and what was
driving me was the fear that it's doing
nothing the the irrational can take over
I love the stoic phrase the obstacle is
the path yeah and I actually love that
you sort of be able to internalize
yourself at that moment when you when
you approach the obstacle that isn't a
moment
you should move back it's actually get
closer and find out more because that's
the way to step over yeah when I was 21
I had the great opportunity to raise a
Timberwolf from 8 weeks old to 2 years
and near in Florida they were incredible
wild highways the 100% Alaskan timber
wolf there I was in Sarasota Florida the
home of the winter home the Ringling
Brothers Circus there was all these
people that had carnivals and people had
wild animal breeders and one of them
would read her so it shut down for the
Humane Society because they weren't
taking care of the animals and the
female wolf was pregnant and had a
litter of eight cub say eight little
wolves and the zoos were full and the
sanctuaries were full and they put them
an ad in the paper for people that they
could apply to see if they thought you
had an appropriate place for a timber
wolf in Florida what's his name they
dress from another book zen and the art
of motorcycle maintenance that's where I
got the name address room and tell us a
bit more about the character Phaedrus in
the book well if he dresses in the
play-doh dialogues and it's it's about
that he's a pert inform the countryside
coming to the city it's about the taming
power of love and in the book Phaedra
says this person who also is takes this
independent way towards quality towards
what he should be doing in his life but
he gets obsessive and he kind of goes
crazy lose perspective and goes through
electroconvulsive therapy and so the
author who's writing the book is writing
from the position of somebody who has
been transformed by electroconvulsive
therapy and is now more grounded and his
prior self was Phaedra's was this no
wild person from the country who was
sort of pure and wild in a way and now
he was having to be worked with him to
contact himself and transform him in
some way yeah and there's a relationship
between his crazy self in a way which
had virtue and his career
self and so vedras was my alter ego in a
way too because I was wanting I felt
like you know I want to get past culture
and why I brought this up was this idea
of the obstacle the way that I built my
I built a house at the edge of town when
I was 21 and there was thousand acres
across the street that was undeveloped
railroad tracks and little ponds kind of
tiny tiny little ponds not a lake for
anything but little hills and different
trees and burned-out areas of the forest
and I could take Phaedra's running
through the woods off leash and there
was a few horses there and some things
but so the way that he moved through the
woods was a lesson to me and I think
about him almost every day something
that because what he would do is he went
straight for his goal and if there was
like a hill in front of it he would just
he has so much energy he would just go
over the hill he would go through bushes
he would just cruise where he wanted to
go and if there was a you know a gully
and stuff you would just go down in that
neuron and you noticed like here there's
a sidewalk in modern society westerns
that there's sidewalks always and
they're not always the most direct way
to get there and sometimes they involve
a tiny bit of an obstacle like in front
of a building there'll be a little hill
but you have to walk way around those
hill but if you just walk over the hill
you'd get there faster and you've had
some exercise so the way he moved
through the world was this sense of
obstacles were opportunities for
exercise and finding he's authentic path
I guess yeah yeah and he had this quiet
confidence one thing I learned about
from him was and it's connected to
psychedelics I was a little bit nervous
about the police at that time and I had
a bunch of big LSD stash and I had a
friend I asked him if he would store it
for me at his house and he had five
acres and a kind of a farm and he had
this big Doberman that wasn't that
friendly but that I knew and so there
was a time I wanted to trip and so I
went over to his house to get some LSD
but he was
there and the Doberman it was like out
back in the barn we're right where the
freezer was but I happen to have the
wolf in my truck and the wolf was just
about five months old or something it
wasn't really you know fully growing or
anything is the and so I thought maybe
there's some way because the wolf a lot
of dogs wouldn't want to play with him
because he was different but some dogs
would so I thought okay I'll get him out
of the truck and just see what happens
and so I um took him off the leash and
he wandered around the barn and he saw
this big door and sort of guarding the
back door where the LSD stash was and he
just wandered around and he saw the DOE
buran and and he just kind of casually
kind of stepped on and just sort of
checked him out and it kind of really
perplexed this Doberman and he just got
up and and walked away from the door and
left the barn and let me go in and get
my honesty stash and you know the
Doberman with this was just they were
big difference in sizes at the time but
it was just this kind of quiet
confidence that this wolf had that I was
trying to absorb and also trying to
realize that the myth is different than
the reality that this was first off
wolves are born with their eyes closed
for a few days and because the Humane
Society knew that this wolf was pregnant
they had taken the Cubs away from the
mother they were prepared for that and
they were raised by people and so when
they opened their eyes they opened their
lives on people so they were kind of
bonded to human beings I love this
aspect of Phaedra's just dispelling this
is the sense of myth of the Doberman
being that the powerful dog or the myth
of the wolf is how a man it was the the
leaping wolves or Wolf's don't really
attack people there are great social
animals they babysit for each other's
kids they one of the best things about
wolves is that in the pack when it's
there's a struggle for dominance and
there's a fight between like a younger
well
reaching maturity and the older wolf
who's in charge that rarely all rarely
rarely does the older wolf get killed
you know they can have these dominant
struggles that change things without
murder so they're incredible animals and
there's something completely different
from this perspective I hats it sound
quite scary Saint Amy taming a wolf yeah
I guess we all we all have these myths
and personal myths and he gets an
important things to recheck these
stories both externally but within
ourselves and that is what allows us to
move through obstacles to move through
blockages in and out in our path yeah
and I knew that the myths of the wolf
were somewhat similar to the myths of
psychedelics that we have these ideas
that these are going to drive people
crazy and that they're and and there's
some situations where that's true but
these are tools to be tamed and used but
tamed in a way where it takes us beyond
the fences of ourselves so it's not
really tamed it's a way to use it to
help us grow in ways we might not
otherwise grow it's about the
relationship you have with them yeah
yeah yeah and so I felt that I I learned
a lot from just seeing how the myth
wolves haven't only rabid wolves have
ever killed people wolves don't attack
people I mean we you know Lions kill
people Tigers kill people but wolves do
not kill me no LSD has never killed a
person not from physically no and people
have done stupid things and people have
died there's and the sentence setting is
very important yeah there's people have
committed suicide under the influence of
psilocybin or LSD out of fear yeah so
certain setting is very important it's
not just certain setting for
psychedelics but I think it's important
to reflect on a certain setting we have
just in our lives it's like a light sky
sensitize ourselves to that very much
and encourage us to be able to change
and shape what we want for ourselves in
the world yeah so um so you've just said
it so very articulately and so
I wonder like what do your parents think
when you talk to them about psychedelics
I'm not sure what liberties I have to
speak here but I'll start with my mom
all right my mom is it was a Catholic
high school teacher very conservative
she actually will say to people at my
talks I you know I grew up teaching
young kids that drugs were bad but I've
seen the changes they have made in my
daughter I think it's very important
that we have these compounds available
for other people who may need them to
heal or to grow my dad Luke trip
together and he's he's a conservative
lawyer Wow
and I feel like they've been able to
heal our relationship with that that
difficult point in a young person's life
when they are trying to outgrow their
parents and come into their own autonomy
we've been able to establish an adult
relationship through the trip we shared
that's beautiful yeah it is really
beautiful and very thankful for them to
be able to allow that transition
wrapping up now I think I think that's a
nice I think cyclic family time is very
important do you want to talk about the
how to educate children or well I think
I also maybe let's start with educating
parents I think the key thing is is that
we have now a very full body of evidence
for the safety of these drugs in the
right set and setting and for the
promise they hold for deepening
relationships both to yourself to the
world and to the people you love we can
now show people their evidence
there's also conversations like this
there's also videos of sessions of
healing for PTSD you thanks to the
availability of that event media from
the trials sure your parents these
things communicate
yeah and we're about to start phase 3 to
have the final evidence that the
regulatory agencies need to make
mdma-assisted therapy for PTSD into
prescription medicine both in the US and
throughout Europe and we're still on
track for 2021 for that is that correct
yeah there's some hurdles some obstacles
that we have to run over and accomplish
ahead but still yeah like failure
slightly we will question I like the
idea of memes and well what would we
like to spread into the world like what
is what is it that we want to leave
behind and if you could I know there's
probably many but if you could just
release one infectious thought one me
mount we can another day but I don't
have one like at the top of my mind I'll
have to think about that just for a
second so let's let's talk about
something else for a moment I am trying
to come up with my daily okay the
obstacle one's important but I guess
let's see I think it's I say that
self-acceptance is the boundary to your
personal freedom that if you can
approach yourself if you can meet
yourself look yourself in the mirror and
recognize who you are right now that's
the next step of becoming who you wish
to be all right so acceptance is the
boundary to freedom that's the one I
would spread out all right so I came up
with one back of my mind so I've been
emailing Stan Grof today earlier this
morning and so what he said something
that I think is so eloquent we talk a
lot about spirituality and you know self
transcendence and there's this idea of
ego death but the ego never really dies
and we're always really watching you
know even in these mystical experiences
somehow there's like a watcher or
something there's still some something
so Stannis said that what we really it's
not so much ego death what we really
need to do is become transparent to the
transcendent yes you know that we're the
filter there were we're still there
there's still this ego sense of who we
are but we can
see so become transparent to the
transcendent
something more expansive behind that I
love the Buddhist concept that that you
know if we sit here now we might feel
maybe your arms gonna be a little tired
or or maybe we remember something but
that which remembers or that that which
feels tired isn't tired there is
something in the largest space of
consciousness that we can find pause and
rest in and I think that's something
that these tools are transformation
psychedelics meditation neurofeedback
can allow us to find in our daily lives
and I think it's very important and
thank you for making this your life's
work and for creating these memes these
are potentials for our future and
engaging in the process and the way that
you have yeah I've been very fortunate
to be able to do this and to have had
these experiences and see change in my
own lifetime and there's more to come as
I said starting off the creative advance
continues yeah thank you thank you
[Music]
and I just wanted to acknowledge the my
gratitude for the marijuana plant which
I consumed smoke some of before our
discussion and I think it helped me be
more emotional more bring more in and it
was a wonderful conversation and and I
have to admit to my transformative tools
of microdose this morning and thirty
minutes of meditation
[Music]
you